JOE: Understanding how an individual with
autism handles information processing,
is a good way to work out how to find the
right strategies to help the individual.
Once their difficulties are identified
then suitable strategies can be introduced
to help with those difficulties.
BETH: Other people such as family
members, teachers, employers, or friends
may need to have a lot of involvement
implementing the strategies, as they may
be used in more than one place; such as
at home, at school or college, or in work.
It is, therefore, important that everyone
involved, uses them consistently.
Some individuals with autism may
develop enough to be able to use the
strategies independently however,
some may always need support.
JOE: Visual references can be a
good way of illustrating what to
do and at what time, but they can
also be helpful in showing the
consequences of an action, such as
missing an appointment or a deadline.
Sequence cards, timers and calendars
can help with structuring the day
at home, in education or work.
BETH: Education and work can cause great
anxiety for everyone when homework,
assignments and deadlines are involved.
Imagine how much more problematic
this is for individuals with
autism, who may have little or no
concept of time and consequences.
JOE: They may need extra help with
using strategies to organise their work,
using lists, calendars and colour coding
to emphasise importance and timing.
Using different coloured files to
identify and clarify importance, can
help with deadlines and making a list
and ticking off as things are completed
in sequence, can help to show progress.
BETH: Processing of instructions can
be difficult, so it may be useful
to use communication books, online
learning environments, and voice
recordings to reduce the pressure on
the individual of trying to remember
what they are supposed to be doing.
Computer programmes, digital calendars
and alerts can also be a reminder for
appointments, deadlines and meetings
and help to keep them on track.
JOE: Like most adults, many individuals
with autism will need to manage their
own money or bills, to varying extents.
Children may have to learn to handle
pocket money, giving them an allowance
and getting them to save with a savings
account, can help as they get older.
Money management apps could be used
to help show how saving works and the
the consequences of not spending
wisely should be stressed.
BETH: Some Individuals with autism
may also need help in understanding
what is the end goal of what
they are working to, with all the
continuous work and deadlines.
Having that goal evidenced
visually will help them to see
this and focus on it going forward.